A Finding Aid to the John White Alexander Papers, 1775-1968, bulk 1870-1915, in the Archives of American Art AAA.alexjohn
Archives of American Art
- Photographs, circa 1870-1915; Series 10; 4.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-8, MGP 1-2, OV 25-43, RD 44-45
  - Portraits of John White Alexander (Box 4)
    - Photographs by Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Copies, circa 1900-1915 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Photographs by Bradley, circa 1913 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Photographs by Elizabeth Buehrman, circa 1909-1912 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Photographs by Elizabeth Buehrman, Copies, circa 1909-1912 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Photograph by Dana (Photography Studio; Brooklyn, NY), circa 1870-1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Photographs by Davis and Sanford, circa 1911 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Photographs by Aimé Dupont, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Photographs by Davis Garber, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Photographs by Miss Huggins, circa 1903-1913 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Photographs by Miss Huggins, Copies, circa 1903-1913 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Photographs by Chester Abbott Lawrence, circa 1904 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Photographs by Pach (Photography Studio, New York), circa 1912 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Photograph by Otto Reitmayer (Photography Studio, Munich), 1877 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Photographs by Rockwood (Photography Studio, New York), circa 1888-1896 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Photographs by Sarony (Photography Studio, New York), circa 1879-1885 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Photographs by Sarony (Photography Studio, New York), Copies, circa 1879-1885 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Photographs by E. Syms, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Photographer Unknown, before 1880 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Photographer Unknown, circa 1890-1909 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      (1 glass plate negative housed in Box 7)
    - Photographer Unknown, circa 1890-1915 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      (2 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 1)
  - Portraits of Others (Box 5)
    - Edward Austin Abbey, circa 1880-1889 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - William Merritt Chase, circa 1870-1879 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Oversized items housed in OV 26
    - Robert Louis Stevenson, circa 1880-1894 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Ruth McEnery Stuart, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified Sitters, undated (Box 5, Folder 24-25)
      (2 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 1-2)
      (Probably subjects of portrait paintings by JWA)
  - Group Portraits and Juries, circa 1900-1915 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Studio, Alexander Memorial Studio at the MacDowell Colony, after 1915; (4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 27) (Box 5, Folder 27-30)
    (includes photographs taken by Jesse Tarbox Beals and Favor Davis; additional photographs and images are found in Awards and Memorials)
  - Studio, New York City, circa 1898-1915 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    (J.W. Alexander pictured)
    (Oversized items housed in OV 27; 3 glass plate negatives housed in Box 7)
  - Studio; Onteora, New York, circa 1913 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Oversized items housed in OV 27
  - Studio, Paris, circa 1892-1898 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Studio; Sea Bright, New Jersey, circa 1888-1908 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1882-1912 (Box 5, Folder 35-37)
    (3 folders; oversized items housed in OV 27; 1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 2)
  - Personal Photographs, Copies, circa 1882-1912 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Polling, Bavaria, circa 1878-1886 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    includes negatives
  - Photographs of Works of Art (Box 5)
    - Installation Views, Art Institute of Chicago, circa 1903, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      Oversized items housed in OV 28
    - Murals (Box 5)
      - Library of Congress Murals (1896), undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Carnegie Institute Murals In Progress, circa 1905-1908 (Box 5, Folder 42)
        (snapshots with workers pictured)
      - Carnegie Institute Murals, Preliminary Drawings, circa 1905-1908 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Carnegie Institute Murals (1905-1908), undated; (4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 28-36; not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 44-47)
      - Carnegie Institute Murals, Lantern Slides, circa 1908-1915 (Box 5, Folder 48)
        (8 lantern slides made by Charles Beseler of New York and identified in what appears to be JWA's handwriting)
        (8 lantern slides housed in Box 8; not scanned)
      - Unidentified Mural, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Paintings (circa 1879-1899), Vintage Prints, undated; (10 of 16 folders; not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 50-59)
    - Paintings (circa 1879-1899), Vintage Prints, undated; (6 of 16 folders; oversized items hosued in OV 37-39; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Paintings (circa 1900-1915), Vintage Prints, undated; 1906; (19 folders; oversized items housed in OV 40-42; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 7-25)
    - Paintings (circa 1898-1904), Recent Prints from Glass Negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Poster, Sculpture, and Drawing (circa 1880-1915), undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Photographs of Works of Art by Others (circa 1880-1899), undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 43, rolled documents 44-45; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 28)
      (includes a portrait of John White Alexander by Frank Duveneck, a portrait of P.W. Bartlett by Charles Sprague Pearce, and around 20 rolled and fragile prints of Rodin sculptures with the note "Given to JWA and EA in Paris circa 1899")
  - Photo Lab Envelopes, undated; 1921; 1910 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of John White Alexander, 1 Glass negatives (Box 7)
    Scanned with Box 5, f18-19
  - Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of John White Alexander, 2 Glass negatives (Box MGP 1)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of Unidentified Sitters, 1 Glass negatives (Box MGP 1)
    Scanned with Box 5, f25
  - Glass Plate Negatives, Portraits of Unidentified Sitters, 1 Glass negatives (Box MGP 2)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, New York City Studio, 3 Glass negatives (Box 7)
    Scanned with Box 5, f31
  - Glass Plate Negative, Personal Photographs, 1 Glass negatives (Box MGP 2)
    Scanned with Box 5, f37
  - Glass Plate Negatives, Paintings, circa 1898-1904; 41 Glass negatives (Box 7)
  - Lantern Slides, Carnegie Institute Murals, Lantern Slides (Box 8 (pam))
  - Oversized Portraits of John White Alexander by Curtis Bell, Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Bradley, Elizabeth Buehrman, Davis and Sanford, Aimé Dupont, Miss Huggins, and Sarony (Box 25 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 4, f42 and 44, Box 5, f1, 2, 5, 6, 8, 14
  - Oversized Portrait of William Merritt Chase (Box 26 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 5, f21
  - Oversized Group Portraits and Juries (Box 26 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 5, f26
  - Oversized Photographs of Studios (Box 27 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 5, f28, 31-33
  - Oversized Personal Photographs (Box 27 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 5, f38
  - Oversized Photographs of Works of Art, Installation Views (Box 28 (OV))
    Scanned with Box 5, f40
  - Oversized Photographs of Carnegie Institute Murals (Box 28-36 (OV))
  - Oversized Photographs of Paintings, Vintage Prints, circa 1879-1899 (Box 37-39 (OV))
  - Oversized Photographs of Paintings, Vintage Prints, circa 1900-1915 (Box 40-42 (OV))
  - Oversized Photographs of Drawings and Poster (Box 43 (OV))
  - Oversized Photographs of Works of Art by Others (Box 43 (OV))
  - Photographs of Rodin Sculptures (Box 44-45 (RD))
- Artifacts, circa 1899-1915; Series 11; 0.4 Linear feet Box 6 and artifact cabinet
  This series contains a variety of objects found among Alexander's papers. The metal door plate reads "J.W. Alexander, Artist" and is signed J.C. Michel and Son. Printing plates are for an ex-libris engraving and two newspaper photographs. Souvenir pendants are from dedications of the Carnegie Institute in 1907 and the New York Public Library in 1911. Title plates from exhibited paintings include one for "Sunlight" and another for a portrait of Mercer Beasley, LLD.
  The bulk of this series has been scanned.
  - Door Plate, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Hand-sewn Book Cover, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Laurel Wreath, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    (See Artifact Cabinet)
  - Palette, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Printing Plates, circa 1915, undated; (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 34-36)
  - Relief Model for Pendant, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Souvenir Engraving of Mark Twain Self-Portrait, 1902 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Souvenir Pendants, 1907; 1911 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    (made for School Art League award; see Awards and Memorials for Alexander's award medal dated 1911)
  - Title Plates from Paintings, circa 1899-1911 (Box 6, Folder 40)